[Music]
[Applause]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se - radio dotnet se Radio
brings you relevant and detailed
discussions of software engineering
topics at least once a month
su radio is brought to you by I Triple E
software magazine online at computer or
/ software are you a tech savvy
developer with an inquisitive mind SC
radio has an opening for a new volunteer
host to join the team and produce five
episodes per year
contact show host Robert bloomin at
Robert bloomin FBL um en at gmail.com
for details
welcome to software engineering radio
I'm Marcus Blankenship and today our
guest is Jerry Weinberg Jerry Weinberg
is a computer scientist author and
teacher of the psychology and
anthropology of computer software
development he's the author of over 30
books including his most recent errors
bugs boo-boos and blunders as well as
the psychology of computer programming
and introduction to general systems
thinking he was manager of operating
systems development in the project
mercury which aimed to put a human in
orbit around the earth welcomed software
engineering radio Jerry thank you good
to be here
before we begin let's make it clear for
people listening what's an error well
that's not an easy thing to answer
because the same thing that is an error
to you might be a feature to me give you
an example I think I have this in the
book well start with something that Alan
Perlis told me years ago and then I
didn't believe for a long time he said
there's no such thing as a wrong
computer program and I thought what you
know that's ridiculous and he said no
there's no wrong programs there's just
different programs and I have to think
about that for quite a while then I
realized
something happened when I was at the
university for a while we were tried to
train computer operators we had the new
multi program machines that would run
more than one program at the same time
so you may be running a dozen programs
and something crashes the machine
crashes the operating system and then
the operator helps at least are all
these dozen programs and it's not an
easy job to do that so we wanted to
train operators to do that but to do
that we needed to have a a program that
would crash the operating system at
random times and then the operator would
have to restart when we tried to write
such a program and we couldn't do it we
just couldn't make it to crash the
operating system at random times and we
were about to give up when somebody
point out that there existed a program
already that did that the physics
department had been working for years to
try to get this big simulation program
going and would Fortran and it had the
property that it didn't do the
simulation they wanted but always crash
the operating system at random times and
that was exactly the training program
that we wanted so for the physics
department it was a wrong program it was
an error to us it was a perfect program
okay so you see why defining what's an
error it's very difficult it depends on
the point of view very subjective of who
was using it so the very same program is
both error or full of errors or perfect
for somebody else
I think that's caused a lot of trouble
and people talking about errors is that
it's not a objective thing and even the
system that crashes the computer might
not be an error you see what I'm saying
yeah and I noticed in the title of your
book you use three different names for
errors maybe this gives us a hint you
use the terms bugs boo-boos and blunders
is is there anything special about those
three names or are you just bringing up
the thought that how we refer to errors
is important somehow it's important
because it's the start of our
investigation into the error in
particular or errors of general starts
with our what we call them and so for
example in the industry it's very common
slang to talk about bugs
all right and the if we're thinking of
bugs and like I have a problem with
pants in my office and you know the ants
come from wherever they come from but I
didn't I think I didn't cause them right
they just decided to occupy my office
and maybe I caused them you know I might
have left a piece of candy around
somewhere or a piece of the sandwich and
they feasted on it but by and large bugs
appear in the world to causes outside of
our own control and if you call thing a
bug it's kind of like I'm not
responsible for this and if I'm not
responsible for this that's the end of
my search to try to prevent it that
makes sense
it does it sounds like when programmers
have told me at times that well the
software worked on their machine so it
must be my problem that it didn't work
on my machine absolutely speaking of
bugs eyes there's an ant crawling across
my keyboard right now okay and how does
that differentiate between things like
boo-boos and blenders which seemed like
a different a different sort of error
yeah exactly so
I'm not sure exactly how you define
those slang terms but a boo-boo is you
know well I I just had a momentary lapse
and don't worry about it they're all
happening again
you know it's it's minor right it's a
little bit Electra baby term boo blender
well yeah I made a big mistake and but
of course I won't do that again because
I don't blunder all the time you know
these are the sort of impressions
they're not exact terms and that's one
of the reasons we try I tried in the
book to come up with you so I didn't I
did invented used terminology that's a
little more precise because the start of
our search for bearers and where they
come from and what to do about them
starts with being clear about what we're
talking about so I used favor of the
terms faults and failures failures are
what we experienced from our and this
program we're using doesn't do what we
hoped it would do it fails and I think
that's fairly clear right it can fail at
different rates it is one plus water
gets three alright that's a probably a
failure unless we're trying to do that
or it takes too long to do the
calculation which is a different kind of
failure but where does the failure come
from there's something wrong in the
program or in the hardware and that's a
fault I like a what causes earthquakes
or false in the earth now that term
isn't perfect but because people think
of fault and they think of blaming it
followed some person and it may not be a
person at all right but it's this it's
the thing inside that causes the failure
outside so if we start to think about
the errors we see it sounds like we can
think about them and start to category
them as either false or failures and oh
no no no see we don't see false if
that's not what we experience a failure
is what we experience fault is where the
experience comes from so if there's a
somebody here who has a manager of a
team that has software and they have a
bug database so they have a list of bugs
that have been reported those are all
experienced failures right and what how
can we begin to I guess maybe work
backwards to find faults is this similar
to what I've heard of every cause
analysis yes that could be if we also I
call it pinpointing where did it come
from exactly and of course there's
different views of that - you could say
okay I've pinpointed a fault defender
came from a line of code that should
have said at a and B and it said it said
subtract a from B so that was the fault
above where did the difference come from
I mean it it didn't just creep into the
Machine somebody wrote the wrong line of
code so where did that come from so you
could say the fault was a human activity
that led to the fault in the software
does that make sense it does I know that
companies I've worked at oftentimes keep
a list of failures but I don't know if
I've seen them keep a list of faults is
it important that companies who want to
improve quality start to pay attention
to both oh yeah well actually the
failures are not ultimately that
important if you want to improve you
have to know where the faults came from
all right then you can change the
process that created these faults okay
or allow them to slip through so for
example and
is a really good example we studied
during Okamoto and I know he was a
student of mine at the University and as
a thesis II he studied the history of
various failures and faults from IBM
operating systems going way back and he
developed the idea of error prone code
where certain pieces of code it seemed
to be full of faults and others were
quite free and so the question - how
come certain pieces of code are much
more troublesome than others and we
figured out some ways to identify them
by analyzing the patterns in the code
but we never figured out how come this
piece of code was more error prone than
this other piece of code some years
later I was talking to capers Jones
about this and he said well what they
had discovered was that the error prone
code was code that had actually skipped
some steps in their code development
process for example or code reviews they
would be in a hurry and they would say
well we don't have time to do this
review and in order to finish our
testing or whatever and lo and behold it
turned out to be the Troublesome things
all right so to correct that you want to
have a process that you're actually
following all the time and I ran into
I'll never forget this any client of
mine I was consulted when I'm trying to
help them find out where they were
getting all their trouble with errors
and I asked them well do you do code
reviews and it said oh yeah we did I
said well when do you do corners is
really almost always still call reduce
and the word almost stuck in my mind and
I said well when
as that you don't do quarter users I'm
thinking this is where they skip a part
of their process and he said well
sometimes the code is late and we're in
a hurry we don't have time to do the
code reviewer okay and that's located
Malvo from dude let's do some root cause
analysis here how come the code is late
and he kind of didn't know why so so
let's go talk to somebody
it's a programmers who have some late
code and we went talked to them and said
how come your code was late tomorrow
because we had a lot of errors in it him
okay and and said so in other words
translating what they were doing when we
had code that had a lot of errors in it
we skipped the part of our process that
was designed to remove errors and once
you get clear easy and you're thinking
about it you start to see stuff okay now
we see what we're doing it's really dumb
and it's sort of the dumbest thing when
you do and I said look if you wanna save
time stop doing code reviews on anything
except the stuff that's late and you'll
get a lot better results I'm not really
recommending that because you never know
when they're gonna have errors but they
were doing exactly backwards or what
they should have been doing and because
they didn't speak clearly about their
errors they didn't think clearly about
theirs
is that all clear absolutely so thinking
clearly and speaking precisely about the
errors takes me to the next question in
the book you assert that these errors
which I've almost always seen lumped
together as bugs there are actually
sources of information and many
companies don't view them that way maybe
you've already answered this but what
kind of information can an errors reveal
and how do we begin learning from them
rather than just trying to sweep them
under the rug well first the mouse we
under the rug you know in other words
not just fix something typically what
happens as an error comes up a failure
comes up and they there's a press-on to
fix it and get it done quickly and get
things going again so the first step is
to extract the information that's there
you know how did this happen and then we
can go and say what are we doing that
will make this happen again in like the
example I just gave if what we're doing
was skipping the step in our process the
error tells us stop skipping this an
error of a pattern of errors that comes
up might tell us there's something wrong
with our training of programmers and
we've had a an example of this with one
client some years ago they kept making
off-by-one errors do you know what I
mean by off by one error yes okay so
they had a lot of these and I have they
weren't doing anything and particularly
about it so I said we'll look together
at the patterns we'll keep doing this
over and over again
how come as I said we back that back up
and said okay we taught our programmers
and we didn't really make it clear how
you terminate a loop all right and so we
modified the training a little bit and a
little special session to update people
and those errors disappeared from a
table
so you look at error and say where did
this come from it's not a bug that just
crept in from the world of nature it's
something that people did and how come
they're doing that okay now I really
like this idea because I think it forces
us as programmers and managers and
people who oversee them to take actual
responsibilities rather than feeling
victimized by these things that creep in
but do you in the past I have actually
expected that my programmers errors were
fully preventable if they would just do
a good enough job I'm wondering if you
think this is a correct view of things
but in another way you're a manager of
programmers and you say if they would do
a good enough job we could prevent
errors well number one you'll never get
perfection and we can't guarantee that
and any by anything we do the laws of
nature tell us that second law of
thermodynamics if you're going to that
tells you but you can get closer and
closer to error free work and it's not
if they'd work better see if you go the
root cause why don't they work better
and it comes back to you the manager
you're not willing to spend the time and
the money to reduce the errors to the
level that you'll be satisfied with but
if you're looking for some kind of
magical free thing I like I'll go in and
I'll give them a lecture or I'll scream
at them or I'll beat them with a stick
or something and now they won't make so
many errors no that's not the way it
goes you give them the resources that
they need and let them know that what
you're striving for and you can reduce
their as low as you want if you're
willing to pay for it in the mercury
project which was the first time that we
ever had a computer program where a
human life was depend about directly I'm
up
were doing we we set a standard to
reduce error we below what anybody had
done before and history of the project
and and those things showed that we were
able to produce an incredible error free
almost error-free piece of software and
for many years it's operated that way
okay but the analysis of them they've
been a few articles about this show that
it costs more than most managers are
willing to spend on their sales analysis
program or their the game program that
they're doing or whatever the I can't
remember the numbers off um they have it
in the book but you know I'd like it
would cost hundreds of dollars per line
of code when you got finished whereas
people don't want to spend them on him
if you're writing a little game that
people will play on their PC or on their
handheld so if it makes an error or two
and you just call it a feature of the
game and why spend all this money and
that's it that's okay you know if that's
what you're doing but if a human life is
resting on the output of this machine
then may be willing to spend more money
but most managers they don't understand
a whole lot of what's going on and one
thing they know how to do is no matter
what you do said well do the same thing
but do it cheaper and anybody can do
that you don't have to be very smart
manager to say that you know just save
us some money or do it faster and put
that back well and do better they don't
know what that means exactly above it so
you're just speaking to the wind when
they do that kind of thing you gotta be
specific yeah here's here's lower do it
better means so and so and then you
can't just do that by saying I want
smaller book count which we hear a lot
you know a lot of people are measuring
their so-called bug count and they say
we reduce the bug count well coming
errors is not as an effective measure
you have to look at the consequence of
some errors and a lot of the problem
comes because of a little owner telling
herself pushing the consequences of
somebody else if you and develop a
product well for example I have a word
processor that I've used years ago that
crashed and lost all my writing you know
if I didn't save regularly you lost all
my writing and it did this at random
times several times a day all right well
that was a failure of the system but it
didn't cost to producers anything it
costs the user something and if you if
you looked at the number of users there
were and how often this kind of thing
was happening it was costing the world
if you like billions or trillions of
dollars okay but the the only way it
would cost the producers was if the word
got out that it wasn't very reliable and
people had alternatives and then they
stopped buying this product then it
would cost them but see now is very
indirect or here I'm writing code today
and two years so now the word comes back
then people are not buying this word
processor because though you had left a
lot of errors in it so go ahead and
change your process now to improve well
it sort of too late now and you've got a
bad reputation so you know it connect
the consequences over there with
anything that you're doing today right
so you mentioned bug count as not being
an optimal way to measure the quality of
then really how well put together your
software is
because as you say you may not be
experiencing that so is there a way to
tell if my team is making too many
errors is there an approach you would
advocate for well I think you it really
depends on the users of the software in
other words you don't know what quality
is unless you're a user of the software
what's quality to one person is
irrelevant to another person I remember
going to Auto Show in New York many many
years ago we were never move out of New
York and living in Manhattan we didn't
own a car and you don't want to have a
car of Manhattan but we were going to
move to Michigan and who we were looking
around for a car so the Auto Show and
we'll touch a good place to go look and
see what's available and walking around
we came to the Rolls Royce exhibit Anna
we weren't in the market for rules who
actually knew that but I couldn't resist
I went over and I ran my hand over the
finish on the rolls and it was a real
experience in xual experience I mean I
read about how many layers of lacquer
they did and how much polishing they did
but I mean the feeling this guy I can
describe it except if you haven't done
it but it was clearly a different level
of finish and I was interested that
because my father was in the auto
painting business and I used to paint
cars so to me this was incredible
quality okay to you who never painted a
car or whatever might think this was
just an extravagance and not worth
anything right so I produce a piece of
software it's like producing a certain
finish on the car you use it and it's
fine it does what I want yeah it fails
once a while but it's not not a big deal
to me
to me the same piece of software might
be totally unacceptable so in order to
really measure the quality of something
you're producing you've got to get a
substitute or a surrogate of your user
somehow you've got to somehow get into
the point of view of the people who will
be using it and try it out and they will
tell you whether it's adequately error
free or low error or whatever we want to
call it but for programmers themselves
to measure it is impossible for the
managers to measure is impossible unless
they are also users of the same software
so if we sort of imagine then that in
the same way as beauty is in the eye of
the beholder
quality is in the eye of the user it
sounds like should we try and measure it
is it something to be measured is it
just something to be asked for our users
opinions how should we approach this
well
asking their opinions is of measurement
you gonna be telling well the word
measurement this thank you sort of
thrown around right again not precisely
and there's old books about measurement
which a lot of study but the word is not
is not used in a precise manner in our
business and what I hear often is this
code of lurid kill them who said to
measure is to know there's you know a
lot of measure of thing then you really
understand it well maybe maybe not I
also liked the quote when people quote
that to me I like to quote back to them
the same Lord Kelvin said back to the
end of the 19th century that it would be
impossible for a heavier-than-air
machine to fly well then let me back up
how can a team who wants to improve
their quality begin to incorporate users
in
to that process and then that's what
they do they're gonna find some users
something some people who represent
their user population and work with them
right
testing out as they go along and
hopefully building incrementally is this
satisfactory to you and it goes both
ways by the way you see the programmers
could be overly critical of their own
code and say it's not very good quality
when in fact their users would be quite
happy with it and I had a client that
was producing something for banks and we
have one bank customer and they were
developing software for that I don't do
too much detail cosign refer keep
confidentiality of Christ but they they
were cuz of errors in their code that
they saw they didn't want to deliver the
code to the bank that was a big customer
and I was call them to help them you
know get rid of it well when they
defined it I was to help them get rid of
these errors right when I came in I said
well let's talk to the bank although
they were afraid to talk to the bank
because they didn't want the bank to
know about all the errors that they made
and we're gonna get him out first and
they were good but that believe that we
would be delivering months behind the
schedule that we had well I said well
let's talk to the bank because it hit a
mediator help side of soften and
everything and they were afraid to Bank
or cancel the contract and everything
well the bankers were very upset because
they weren't getting delivery of this
thing and I explained to them well they
don't want to deliver because of have
certain errors and they said well we
don't care we're not gonna actually use
the thing in in the bank until we train
all our tellers how to use it and we can
train them with the software that has
these programmer errors in it
we can train their own take months to
train them and if it makes a few errors
in the training it doesn't matter but if
we don't have it to use then we can't
train them and then when the time comes
to install it they won't be trained and
that won't be in here so you see here
the programmers were thinking the sting
was of not of adequate quality the bank
was thinking it was not delivered on
time it was a prime quality for training
purposes so you see without actually
contacting and this is just thing I see
over and over again programmers often
their managers don't want to talk to
their users and they have all kinds of
reasons
they're afraid like this case the users
will see it errors we made in the
process that we correct but that we
don't want them to see that we made any
errors at all or they are worried that
if we talk to our customers our users
they will keep asking for more features
and we won't be able to control this
well that's where you start if you want
really quality stuff you have to have
contact with the people who are going to
tell you whether it's quality or not
I mean emphasis and seem to require a
brilliant mind to figure that out but it
seems to be something we don't do I like
what you said about people wanting the
customer or the user to have the
impression that something has no errors
at all I see this a lot as well and that
also delays delivery as well as creates
a huge apprehension that if the person
who I'm showing it to you sees an error
they will have a negative reaction
towards me but do you think we should be
representing the software as error-free
is that something that's that we should
do no I years ago my mind is going in
several directions and once years ago
and
eeehm they have the IBM 650 computer
which is one of the first ones that I
worked with and it was based on vacuum
tubes so that in those days before
transistors the machines made more
errors than they do now and I bmm of
sales slogan that said IBM 650 have
never made an undetected error
that's quite a sales pitch yeah it is
but if you think about it you realize
it's totally meaningless drivel but how
do we they know if if you had an
undetected error how would you know you
have it because you couldn't detect it
in you know so so of course that's the
sales pitch but we'd be better off all
right now that may be another thing I
thought of when I first got married and
my father gave me a piece of advice
which I'll never forget he said if your
wife and they first even knows these he
was sewing or the woman did all the
cooking and so on you know which is not
exactly modern twenty-two but he said if
your wife cooks a meal for you and you
don't like it tell her that don't hide
that because you love her and you don't
want to feel bad and this and that
tell her otherwise you're going to get
the same meal over and over again
through your whole married life
all right you see the relevance of them
I do and as a married person I can say I
would agree with that telling your wife
the fifth time you didn't like it is
received far differently than the first
time mm-hmm
you know same thing if you don't have
this feedback connection with the
producers of what you're eating or using
as a software then it does not gonna get
any better
absolutely so I'm curious have you seen
that switching topics here a bit are
there some languages or technologies
that are less error prone than
there's no just flat no no I mean the
technology is relevant it isn't I
suppose you could be using a compiler
have capita lots of errors in the
compiler but I mean the tools that we
use it's how you use them I mean it's
like if I have a mind into the leg and
my left leg a huge scar from where
somebody knocked a circular saw into my
leg many years ago it gave me a unique
experience of being able to see the bone
in my leg through this open wound but
the lesson I learned from that is that
any tool can be used in a harmful way
it's not the tool it's the way you use
it we used to write code in binary and
we often produce a relatively error-free
code because the way we things we did to
make sure and one of the things that
yeah I suppose a tool could encourage
you we were worried when people started
working with terminals and going online
time-sharing systems that programmers
could correct errors so quickly that
they would get careless and that happens
some programmers our Caliph's are
working with a pc eater that and okay i
just write anything and if it's wrong
I'll fix it later because that's heard a
reasonably but we had a turnaround time
we were in California and our computer
was in New York City this was before jet
planes we would fly a box of punch cars
to New York and I would be picked up at
the airport and taken to downtown and
the run on the computer and when we get
the result be punched in the current
boxing mailed on a plane back to us in
California and took about a week to turn
it around so to us the consequences of
making a mistake was a delay of a whole
week and then we thought if you just sit
there at the machine and fix things as
on the fly then there's no real
consequence to you as a programmer to
making mistakes and so you'd get
careless and sure enough some
programmers working on a Mac or PC are
very careless I produce a lot of errors
do a lot of correcting and they tend to
leave a lot more errors in because they
have more to begin with but other
programmers can work with great
discipline at a PC or Mac mmm don't do
that so it isn't the environment it
isn't the tools the compilers the
testing tools and make these errors it's
the people and how they use them the
same way I mean I go into a shop and I
not anymore but I used to be did a lot
of woodworking a lot of carpentry and
some furniture building and so on
and I don't a place not see somebody
taking a chisel and opening a paint can
with it and I would just make me shudder
I mean it's a misuse of a tool but it is
it the chisels fault that some is
usually drove on a paint can know right
yeah absolutely
another part that I hear a lot of people
talk about when it comes to quality and
bugs and errors is test automation do
you view that as something that's really
reduced errors dramatically no there's
how you use the particular kind of
automation or use it or I tell people
about automation is it's an effort
reducing thing
you could do everything that automation
does by hand right but it will cost more
to do it automation make certain parts
of testing easier and cheaper all right
when it's easier and cheaper you can do
things faster and it could make you
careless or it could be used very well
either way and I've seen both things
happen with this automation
it's like friend of mine another
woodworker and they've got a new power
saw and I said oh it's great it makes
you know better where this is really
actually what it does it makes it
possible to make a lot of scrap wood a
lot faster okay
mmm test automation could do that if you
don't know what you're doing when you're
testing you get a tool to do it faster
then you just make mistakes faster some
people use test automation tools as if
it's wonderful database to set down in
advance all these tests that somehow
before they know what they're doing is
going to test the exotically and you
can't do that
generally speaking you can't do that I
mean yes we want to test first and
that's something we've always preached
and always done is think in advance how
you're going to test something right but
don't waterfall it that's because you
think in advance to do the best you can
and then you adapt as you go along you
say oh well we tested all this stuff we
automated these tests but look at what
we've missed or what were missing we're
not going to see this kind of error
we're not roasted so we do
context-driven
testing plus automation where we can and
all these things come down to people
looking for magic solution right any
trail managers will just say test
everything you know well anybody could
say that right that would be wonderful
if you could do it there's nothing wrong
with wanting to do
but you can't do it it's impossible even
the simplest program to test everything
any program you've got some of you want
a program and you tell me here's how
we're going to test it and I can write a
program in such a way that your tests
will miss the mistakes that it's making
to always do that and something that
we've known Charles Babbage and I are
junior listeners know Charles Babbage
was if they don't they should look it up
150 years ago knew this right that you
could you could never test quality into
a program you could do it any number of
tests and I'm gonna how many tests you
did literally millions and billions of
tests you could always miss some error
some Fault in the program so testing has
to be adaptive
it cannot be 100% automated that makes
sense and the last few answers you've
given me have a theme that the people
involved are very important that tools
and process and there is no silver
bullet or magic answer so I'm curious
what advice do you have for engineers
who might be listening who want to
create fewer errors in their own work
first thing pops into my mind is the
slogan many ice makes fewer errors right
nobody that I've ever met and and I've
got some incredible programmers nobody
is good enough to see all the mistakes
that they made so you want to get other
people involved the various ways of
doing this but you could have to be open
to feedback and seek feedback from other
people just like you know I write a book
and I think it's terrific guy so I wrote
a paragraph I just really explain
something I don't know if it really does
that unless I test it on other people
right
so expose your work to as many other
peoples are willing to give it a good
look alright related to that is of
course use use whatever tools you've got
expose it to the court eyes of the tools
but don't come out as that's all you
have to do when I was just meeting
programming team for example in the
mercury project we have a guy that was
supposed to be really good but he didn't
like our ideas of redoing each other's
code and I had to release him from the
project it wasn't good enough I had a
client where we introduced our various
methods of doing this or Unicode testing
other people's work and there's a little
bit a large number of programmers five
or six hundred and three of them said
they wouldn't do this so nobody can look
at my work I'll be outlook of other
people's work but nobody can look at my
work it's like somehow my work there's a
trap
it isn't your as you're doing it for
somebody else right
yes if I'm writing a piece of code here
on my own machine for my own use I can
do whatever I want I can have errors in
in there I can love it it doesn't matter
right but if you're working on a job
building code for somebody it doesn't
belong to you you're being paid to
produce it so they have three but they
have three guys all guys who wouldn't
accept this and so they didn't know what
to do Avengers didn't know what to do it
ISIF here's what we'll do we'll accept
that they say this Hitler but you know
eat soon I don't make mistakes
I said okay here's a little you can work
by yourself you don't have to use the
methods that we're talking about you
don't have to have this feedback but if
one of the pieces of code that you write
makes an error
and it costs us a certain amount then
we'll deduct that from your salary hmm
well there's said that to the three guys
first one said okay I see what you're
saying I'll do what you want I mean he
realized at some level they're his ego
wasn't it was a little overstated and he
couldn't afford you know to have to pay
for his errors the second one second the
other two said okay you know we'll do
that right so first of all of them the
first program that he wrote failed cost
them a substantial amount of money and
they came to him and they said well all
of you now owe us more than you're gonna
earn in the next few years but we'll be
glad to let you go and without paying
then ah and so he was gone which they
realized was a good thing the sky was
sprinkling errors and everything ahead
and taking no responsibility for them so
the third guy took the deal and he
produced it for over six months he
produced various pieces of code and
nothing ever went wrong with them you
know I mean this guy was really good and
he was one of the handful of the very
best programmers then I had ever run
across and it worked very precisely he
had his own methods right which were
very sophisticated but he didn't let
other people look at his work but then
finally I think it was a seven or eight
months he had one little mistake that
happened to wipe out a important
database and they came to this is look
you know either gonna have to work for
the rest of your life for free based on
this deal that we have you know what do
you want to do and it was they thought
they could do what they did with the
second guy and just fire him right but
then I thought you know he's really good
he really knows a lot he's not perfect
he's a human being so we made a deal and
we said look you see what happened
you don't make very many mistakes much
better than everybody else so we want to
use you to train the other people to
work than what you do precisely within
the system that we were propagating of
reviewing and so on
and if you do that with what we won't
charge you all this money and and he he
saw the logic of it and he agreed if he
became an extremely valuable employee to
the organization so did that kind of
thing has happened over and over again
but if funny you know it's a matter of
personality you know certain people are
not cut out for being a programmer that
works at a low error environment and
they invisibly program anymore I mean if
you have a surgeon who had palsy or
something and couldn't steady his hands
or her hands you know they might have
good intentions they may be nice people
but they just don't have what it takes
to be a good surgeon and they'd be
killing patients right right now that
makes sense in that same theme of
exposing your work do you see that open
source software that that movement has
yielded increased quality it hasn't some
pieces I mean they're low again a little
from sources is a blank of term and it
covers a lot of different ways that
things are done
but the concept has the possibility of
producing much lower error rates than
some of the other traditional ways that
that things are done I mean in a way you
see agile first of all is team based
open source is team based but in either
case and team means that more than one
set of eyes is looking at everything
right you know so you can you can have a
team where the people don't really work
together as a team by calling it a team
doesn't make it a team and calling you a
leg doesn't make you a lady calling an
opensource doesn't make it really open
to you know again some of the open
source projects that I've seen now
really like one person is doing it and
other people look at it but they don't
listen to what they have to say or they
don't look at it carefully you know you
must have had the experience you're
reading a book and sort of wake up and
say you know I'm ten pages past four
hours before why don't I just read a
sentence you know what I mean you know
change your mind has to be engaged in it
and looking at code is the same thing
right you have to engage your line so
rather than what I look for in trying to
build a good programming process is
people who know how to engage their
minds and what they're doing who know
how to recognize it see the team is not
just looking at the code but they're
looking at each other and what they're
doing and so that said you know I did
review this but it was a bad day my dog
was sick and
your credit card company said I owe them
a lot of money and I well these things
are of my mind and now I passed my eyes
over this piece of code but I wasn't
really engaged in it so you can't really
rely when I said let's do it over again
okay and that's human beings I mean
that's what we do absolutely I think
we've learned the the pitfall of
trusting in magic labels like open
source and agile and automation and
really heard that it comes down to the
individual and their approach and the
their willingness to accept their own
imperfections no I like the way you said
that as we wrap up here do you see any
trends coming that will radically change
software quality maybe in the next 10 to
20 years okay so let's start answering
again with the same or even the term
software is a broad term and covers
millions of things when Apple came out
with the iPad there had said that there
were six hundred thousand programs for
the iPad six hundred thousand pieces of
software now do you think they were all
the same that's an excellent point I
have used that term very broadly yeah
and so software I think what's happening
is where people their management of
whatever understands the need for a
certain level of quality and is willing
to put into getting it what is required
then we're going to we're getting higher
quality stuff where they don't you know
they don't realize what they need to
have a saleable product or a usable
probably or they realize it but they
don't they're not willing to spend or
then and then we're not going to give
higher quality now where they do realize
it and they're willing to spend then the
knowledge that we have about how to do
it becomes relevant but if you're not
willing to do it it doesn't matter if
you know how to do it right I mean I
there's been some discussion recently
about some of my books on Twitter and
stuff and I'm if several people have
told me they said oh yeah your book you
know people say oh Jerry's books are
wonderful blah and so oh yeah I bought
this book I haven't read it it's like oh
you mean if you buy the book somehow you
get better
I'd like to convince people that because
I'd make a lot of money and all you have
to do is buy my book and then you'd be
smarter but you do have to actually read
it and the same thing with these ideas
about quality test automation agile
teams whatever this tool or that's what
whatever it is doing the name and saying
the name doesn't improve your quality at
all it's like putting the book under
your pillow and exactly expecting all
the knowledge to come up because you
know that you know the new magic word it
would be great I mean it would be
wonderful if you do that right I get a
lot more books read yeah Jerry is there
anything I've forgotten to ask you
anything where you'd like to add as
we're wrapping up well I'm sure there's
things you forgot right we know that
from our whole discussion I am imperfect
and there are things that I've forgotten
to tell you all right so it's a
continuing process I guess those type
maybe conclude by saying if you want it
if you're a programmer or for listening
to this or tests or service or manager
this leaders the big lessons commit
yourself to getting feedback and
continuously using that feedback
discarding some of it it doesn't apply
but engaging web and then modifying your
behavior
keep improving your whole life long I
mean I've been in the software business
the the computer business for over now
70 years now sorry when I was a computer
and I'm just better now than I used to
be because I keep looking to improve
when I look for assignments and I'm
asking myself will I learn things in
this assignment if I won't then I'll do
something else so commit yourself to
continuous learning and realizing you'll
never be perfect but you'll get better
and better
wonderful okay where can people find
more about yiling your work and your
bets will probably just go to my website
to start so you're actually not just my
website and there was a a very nice
there's a couple people who sort of
follow my work and they have interviews
with me and lists of various books and
articles and so on so there's my website
and Gerald my burg calm it's important
to have the M for my middle initial
because some pirates have taken the
citement
Gerald Weinberg without the M and
they're selling some junk there well
we'll print put the links in the show
notes okay Gerry thank you for joining
us today
forgive remoting know some fun
I hope it's useful to people I'm sure it
will be thanks for listening to se radio
an educational program brought to you by
I Triple E software magazine for more
information about the podcast including
other episodes visit our website at se -
radio name to provide feedback you can
write comments on each episode on the
website or write a review on iTunes
mention a message us on Twitter
at SC radio or search for the software
engineering radio group on LinkedIn
Google+ or Facebook you can also email
us at team @ SC - radio net this and all
other episodes of SU radio is licensed
under the creative commons 2.5 license
thanks again for your support
[Music]
you